Guide to the Romeyn Berry family papers, 1636-1960.
Berry, Romeyn family papers, 1636-1960.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Romeyn Berry family papers, 1636-1960.
2531
Romeyn Berry, 1881-1957.
1.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, diaries, journals, drawings, photographs, legal documents, newspaper clippings, a scrapbook, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers of Romeyn Berry, a columnist, author, lawyer, and farmer.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Columnist, author, lawyer, farmer.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence includes personal and business correspondence; Berry's letters from Kenneth Roberts, E.B. White, and Allison Danzig; one letter from Major William B. Miles concerning the activities of the Seventh Regiment, New York National Guard; correspondence of Berry's second wife, Hester Bancroft Berry, her father, Wilder D. Bancroft, and other members of the Bancroft family. Writings include copy and clippings from his "Talk of the Town" columns in The New Yorker; articles from the Ithaca Journal and Cornell Alumni News; radio broadcasts; and books and pamphlets by others. Diaries and journals by Berry, Katherine Bott Bancroft, and Hester Bancroft Berry, 1943-1951; farm accounts from "Stoneposts," Jacksonville, N.Y., 1936-1938; drawings; family and other photographs; legal documents and related items referring to the Berry and Gould families; newspaper clippings relating to Professor Wilder D. Bancroft; items having Ithaca or local interest, including Lyceum Theater accounts, 1893-1923; and miscellaneous family items. Also, student scrapbook of Olive Nutting Berry at Wells College, with material about social events at Cornell University.
Also, correspondence between Romeyn Berry, his grandmother Hannah Wright Gould, his mother, and others, mostly when he was an undergraduate at Cornell; condolence letters after Berry's death, written to his widow Hester Bancroft Berry, to his daughter, Hilda Berry Sanford, and to Ruth Berry McDonald; program from the memorial stone dedication in 1988; magazine and newspaper articles; trust agreement; and typescript version of Hannah Wright Gould's 1871"Garden Journal," with a pen-and-ink drawing on wood of Romeyn and Harriet Berry as children.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Berry, Romeyn, 1881-1957.; Bancroft family.; Bancroft, Katherine Bott.; Bancroft, Wilder D. (Wilder Dwight), 1867-1953.; Berry family.; Berry, Hester Bancroft, 1899-1963.; Berry, Olive Nutting.; Danzig, Allison.; Roberts, Kenneth Lewis, 1885-1957.; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-; Cornell University--Students.; Lyceum Theater (Ithaca, N.Y.); Wells College--Students.
Titles:
New Yorker
Subjects:
Farms--New York (State)--Jacksonville.; Family--New York (State); Women college students.; Journalists.; Lawyers.; Authors.
Form and Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Account books.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Drawings.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Writings by Romeyn Berry and others
Series III. Pamphlets and books
Series IV. Journals and accounts
Series V. Drawings and photographs
Series VI. Legal documents and related items
Series VII. Newspaper clippings
Series VIII. Miscellaneous
Series IX. Scrapbooks
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Correspondence (Box 1)
  Letters to George and John C. Bancroft (the letter to George appears to be from John, but the last page is missing) of May 11 and 12, 1881, concerning the will of Abisha Larned of Oxford, Mass., a copy of the will, and other relevant information; a letter from Peter Cantine (location?) to Charles F. Mulks (Ithaca), Jan. 15, 1895, re: Cantine's family genealogy, which Mulks had apparently requested, and in turn requesting information from Mulks in order to "prove" the will of a Samuel W. Ransom; two letters to Wilder D. Bancroft from Mark A. DeWolfe Howe (July 15 and Dec. 14, 1904); fifteen letters (Nov. 20-23, 1906) from various British scientists to Sir William Ramsay, regarding Wilder Bancroft's suggestion that the Journal of Physical Chemistry be published in England; letters to Hester Bancroft in Europe (ca. 1926), including a letter from Morris Bishop (Feb. 18, 1926); and other letters to Hester and Romeyn Berry, pertaining to Hester Berry's sculptures, the launching of the U.S.S. Bancroft, publication of Romeyn's work by Putnam's, and other topics. Also a printed Christmas card from Sir Wilfred and Lady Grenfell (n.d.) and a Christmas card from a drawing by Hester Berry (May 11, 1881-Mar. 31, 1953, 38 pcs.).
  Correspondence, mostly to Hester Bancroft Berry and her brothers, sisters, and other relatives, regarding the disposition of the Wilder Bancroft and other family estates, the John Chandler Bancroft art collection, and other related items (Sept. 12, 1952-May 27, 1954 and n.d., 31 pcs.).
  - Family letters to and from Romeyn Berry as Cornell student (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Condolence letters (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Letter and trust document to Miss Berry (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series II. Writings by Romeyn Berry and others
  - Clippings from "State and Tioga," Berry's column in the Ithaca Journal Also one reprint of a column., ca. 1931-ca. 1956 (Box 1)
  - Clippings from "Now, In My Time," Berry's column in the New Yorker magazine's "Talk of the Town" section (n.d., approx. 100 pcs.). (Box 1)
  - "Accommodations for Visitors," (reprinted from Cornell-Colgate official program, 1 pc.)., Oct. 1, 1949 (Box 1)
  - "Dee Day on the Dirt Roads," by Berry, 4 pp. mimeographed. (Box 1)
  - "Reading Books for Fun," by Berry, 8 pp. carbon typescript. (Box 1)
  - "Berry Junction - All Out for Eating," by Alice B. Kline and Lila M. Jones, 3 pp. carbon typescript. (Box 1)
  - A list of articles by Berry (2 pp. carbon typescript)., 1938-1948 (Box 1)
  - A notebook of poetry (handwritten) by Hester Bancroft. Also 5 single sheets, handwritten and typewritten, of her poems (n.d.). (Box 1)
  - A notebook of poems written about or during World War I compiled by Hester Bancroft. (Box 1)
- Series III. Pamphlets and books
  - The Architectural Record (57:3), Mar. 1925 (Box 2)
  - Brookgreen Gardens History (South Carolina: Brookgreen Gardens,) 31 pp., 1959 (Box 2)
  - A Century of Growth, Meadowbrook Nurseries. One of 1000 copies printed, inscribed to Romeyn Berry., 1845-1945 (Box 2)
  - Cornell Annual Horse Show 36 pp., 1923 (Box 2)
  - Cornell Widow Contains article on Berry., Nov. 1947 (Box 2)
  - Family History of the Berrys and the Goulds (33 pp., offset printed and in a spiral notebook. The same history can be found in #2027). (Box 2)
  - Intercollegiate Association of Amateur Athletes of America, Sourvenir Volume. Ed. by Edward Bushnell (: I.A. of A.A.A.) 122 pp., 1914 (Box 2)
  - The Lantern (Westover School magazine), Mar. and Apr. 1918 (Box 2)
  - A Modern Pilgrim's Bayshore Guide ( 28 pp.), 1935 (Box 2)
  - Romeyn Berry memorial (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Article about Romeyn Berry, Princeton Alumni weekly (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series IV. Journals and accounts
  - A European travel diary kept by Katherine Bott (later Mrs. Wilder Bancroft) in the summer of, 1880 (Box 2)
  - Romeyn Berry's diaries, 1943-1951 (Box 2)
  - "Greenhouse Diary," a small partially filled notebook kept by Hester Berry, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Hannah Gould Garden Diary, 1871 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lyceum Theater accounts, 1893-1923 (Box 2)
  - "Stoneposts - Stock on Hand," a book kept by Hester Berry - egg, cream sales, etc., 1936-1938 (Box 2)
  - A small notebook partially filled with notes on animal diseases and notations "Stock Book" (owner unknown)., 1940 (Box 2)
- Series V. Drawings and photographs
  - Two family photograph albums, 1920 (Box 3)
    One containing pictures of Ithaca and Cornell people
  - Approximately 80 photographs and negatives of Romeyn, Hester, and Warner Berry, Gettysburg in 1954, and other subjects, 1954 (Box 3)
  - 3 oversized comic photographs of "boxers," including Berry and Robert Elias Treman, Date unknown (Box 3)
  - Photograph portrait of George Bancroft, Date unknown (Box 3)
  - Approximately 50 photographs of sculptures by Hester Bancroft Berry, Date unknown (Box 3)
  - Approximately 55 water colors, washes, oils, etchings, and pencil and charcoal drawings, many of foreign scenes, 1890's, undated (Box 3)
    Artist unknown
  - Approximately 30 reproductions of pen and ink drawings (etchings?) by Daubigny, Corot, Rousseau, and other artists, Date unknown (Box 3)
  - Watercolors and a print of a bird, 1880's-1890's (Folder 2)
- Series VI. Legal documents and related items (Box 4)
  Berry's birth certificate, Armed Services Honorable Discharges, Certificate of Promotion to First Lieutenant (5 pcs.); the will of Wilder D. Bancroft (1939, carbon typescript, 7 pp.); inventory of Wilder Bancroft estate items [Appears to be restricted to art objects displayed and stored at the Worcester Art Museum, Worcester, Mass. Acc. Nos. given by each item. 1953.]; and agreement settling the estate of Harriet V.V. Berry; the final settlement of the account of Romeyn Berry, as executor of the will of Elisabeth W. Berry; a return receipt from the postmaster and a typed paper listing items received from Romeyn Berry as Trustee of the Sarah Gould Estate (June 7, 1927 and n.d.); Romeyn Berry's life insurance policy with the Traveler's Company; bankbooks, estate loan, signed by J.R. and Effie Turner (Apr. 12, 1916); a deed between Wesley W. and Alice S. Warsaw and Olive Lee Berry (Aug. 20, 1919); an assessor's list for the town of Ulysses (1867), and other items. See also Correspondence for further items pertaining to the Wilder Bancroft and other family estates.
- Series VII. Newspaper clippings (Box 4)
  Clippings (25 items) from many newspapers relating to Professor Wilder Bancroft's experiments in rain-making (1923); a page from the Ithaca Journal about early explorers and travellers in Tompkins County (Jan. 26, 1955); and other items.
- Series VIII. Miscellaneous
  - Berry family tree, Date unknown (Box 4)
  - 5 pp. of biographical data concerning Warner ("Butch") Berry's first three years of life, Date unknown (Box 4)
  - "History of the Village of Brookton" (dictated by Cantine Lounsbery, July 11, 1907, 2 pp. typescript), 1907-07-11 (Box 4)
  - U.S. Geological Survey Map of New York - Ithaca Quadrangle, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Other miscellaneous items, Date unknown (Box 4)
  - Indenture - Yorkshire, 1636 (Folder 1)
  - Indenture - Lancashire, England, 1691 (Folder 1)
- Series IX. Scrapbooks
  - Olive Nutting Berry scrapbook, with invitations to social functions at Cornell University and elsewhere, programs, postcards, photographs; Wells College material including a manual, constitution and by-laws and two copies of the Wells College Chronicle, correspondence, poetry from Romeyn Berry to Olive, formal announcement of the their wedding, calling cards, a copy of the Cornell Alumni News and photographs of fraternity parties at Cornell., 1902-1912 (Box 5)
  - Printed items removed from Olive Nutting Berry scrapbook (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Olive Nutting Berry scrapbook items, loose, 1903-1909 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Olive Nutting Berry loose items (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Olive Nutting Berry, loose pages (Box 5, Folder 4)